In this video, we're going to take a look at hooks.
この動画では、フックについて見ていきます。
These allow you to run commands before or after Claude
これらを使うと、Claudeがツールを実行する前後にコマンドを実行できます。
attempts to run a tool. Hooks can be used to implement
フックは、非常に興味深く、非常に有用な機能を実装するために使用できます。
really interesting and very useful functionality.
例えば、Claudeがファイルを書き込むと決定した後、
For example, after Claude decides to write a file,
作成されたファイルに対して自動的にコードフォーマッタを実行したり、
you can automatically run a code formatter on
ファイルを編集した後にテストを実行したり、
the created file, or you can run tests after
特定のファイルへのアクセスをClaudeにブロックさせたりできます。
a file is edited, or you can block Claude
可能性は本当に無限大で、いくつかの良い例を用意しました。
from reading particular files. The possibilities
皆さんの特定のプロジェクトでフックをどのように使用できるか、
are really endless, and I've got a couple of good
いくつかのアイデアを紹介します。
examples lined up to show you some ideas of
まず、フックがどのように機能するかを正確に理解していただくために説明します。
how you might use hooks on your particular project.
思い出していただきたいのですが、Claude Codeに何かを要求すると、
First, however, let me help you understand exactly how
そのクエリは、いくつかのツール定義とともにClaudeモデルに送信されます。
hooks work. As a reminder, when you ask Claude
Claudeモデルは、慎重にフォーマットされた応答を提供することで、
code something, your query is sent off to the Claude model
ツールを実行すると決定するかもしれません。そしてその時点で、
along with some tool definitions. The Claude model
Claude Codeが要求されたツールを実行し、
might then decide to run a tool by providing a carefully
この場合はファイルを読み取るかもしれませんが、
formatted response. And at that point,
そのツールの呼び出し結果で応答します。
it is up to Claude code to run the requested tool, maybe
フックを使用すると、ツール実行の直前または直後に
in this case to read a file, and then respond with the result
コードを実行する機能が得られます。
of that tool call. Now hooks give
ツール実行の前に実行されるフックは、
us the ability to execute code just before
「プリツールユースフック」と呼ばれます。なぜなら、ツールより前に実行されるからです。
or just after the tool execution.
そして、ツール実行の後に実行されるフックは、
Hooks that run before a tool are referred to as
「ポストツールユースフック」と呼ばれます。同じ理由からです。
pre-tool use hooks because they run before
フックを定義するには、Claude Settingsファイルに設定を追加します。
the tool. And hooks that run after the tool are
いくつかの異なる設定ファイルがあることを思い出してください。
referred to as post-tool use for the same reason.
1つは、お使いのコンピューター上のすべてのプロジェクトでグローバルに使用されるものです。
To define hooks, we add configuration to the Claude
1つは、他のエンジニアと共有される、お使いの特定のプロジェクト用のものです。
Settings file. Remember that there are several different
そして1つは、特定のプロジェクトでお使いいただくためだけのものです。
settings files, one for global use across all
フックを追加するには、このファイル内に手書きで記述するか、
projects on your machine, one for your particular project
Claude Code自体内の組み込みのスラッシュフックコマンドを使用して追加できます。
that gets shared with other engineers, and one for just you
設定自体は、画面右側に見えるような形になります。
on a particular project. You can add hooks,
この例のファイルを見ていきましょう。
either by writing them out by hand, inside
まず、このファイル内には2つの異なるセクションがあることに注意してください。
this file, or by using the built-in slash hooks
1つのセクションには、ツール使用の前に実行されるすべてのコマンドがリストされています。
command inside of Claude Code itself. The
これらはプリツールユースフックと呼ばれます。
configuration itself looks like what you see on
もう1つのセクションには、ツール使用後に実行されるすべての
the right-hand side of the screen. Let me walk you through this example
さまざまなコマンドがリストされています。
file just to give you a better idea of what's going
そしてこれも、ポストツールユースフックと呼ばれます。
on. So first, notice that there are two
これらの各セクションで、マッチャーを提供します。
distinct sections inside of this file. One
これは、どのツール使用タイプを探しているかを示します。
section lists out all the commands that should be executed before
この場合、読み込みツールの使用を見つけたいです。
a tool use. Remember, those are referred to as pre-tool
Claude Codeがファイルを読み込もうとするたびに、
use hooks. The other section lists out all the different
そこでリストされているコマンドを実行したいと思います。
commands that should be executed after a tool
同様に、ポストツールユースセクション内では、
use. And again, those are post-tool use hooks.
書き込み、編集、またはマルチ編集ツールの使用後に、
In each of these sections, we provide a matcher. This
実行したい別のコマンドがあります。
indicates which tool use types we are looking for.
さて、重要な部分です。
So in this case, I want to find uses of the read
フックが本当に意図されていることはこれです。
tool. Whenever Claude Code attempts to read
先ほど見たコマンドには、Claudeが実行したいツール呼び出しに関する詳細が提供されます。
a file, I want to run the command you see listed
プリツールユースフックの場合、Claudeが何をしたいかを検査できます。
there. Likewise, inside the post tool
そして、何らかの理由で許可したくない場合は、
use section, after a use of the write, edit,
ツール使用操作をブロックし、エラーメッセージをClaudeに返すことができます。
or multi-edit tools, there's a different command
ポストツールユースフックの場合、ツール呼び出しは既に発生しているので、
that I want to run. Now, here's the important part.
ブロックするには遅すぎます。
Here's what hooks are really intended to do. Those
しかし、ツール呼び出しに基づいたフォローアップ操作を実行できます。
commands you saw will be given details about the tool call
例えば、編集されたばかりのファイルをフォーマットするようなことです。
that Claude wants to run. In the case of a
また、そのツール使用についてClaudeにメッセージを返すこともできます。
pre-tool use hook, you can inspect what
例えば、コードの品質をチェックするために別のプログラムを実行することを決定したり、
Claude wants to do. And if for any reason
型チェックを行ったりするかもしれません。
you don't want to allow it, you can block the tool use operation
そして、そのフィードバックをClaudeに返します。
and send an error message back to Claude. In
Claudeは、そのフィードバックを受け取って、
the case of a post tool use hook, the tool call
書き込んだばかりのファイルに更新を加えるかもしれません。
has already occurred, so it's too late to block it. But
フックについて、またはフックが何を意図しているかについて、まだ混乱している場合は、
you can do some follow-up operation based upon the tool
それは全く問題ありません。フックを理解するのは非常に難しいことがあります。
call, like maybe format a file that was just edited.
ですので、しばらくお待ちいただいてから、
You can also provide some message back to Claude about
フックを使ったサンプルプロジェクトで作業しましょう。
that tool use. For example, you might decide to
例えば、コードの品質をチェックするために別のプログラムを実行することを決定したり、
run a separate program to check the code quality
型チェックを行ったりするかもしれません。
of the edit, or maybe do a type check,
そして、そのフィードバックをClaudeに返します。
and then provide that feedback back to Claude. Claude
Claudeは、そのフィードバックを受け取って、
might then take that feedback and make an update
書き込んだばかりのファイルに更新を加えるかもしれません。
to the file that it just wrote to. If you're still
フックについて、またはフックが何を意図しているかについて、まだ混乱している場合は、
confused about hooks or what they are intended to do, that
それは全く問題ありません。フックを理解するのは非常に難しいことがあります。
is absolutely okay. Wrapping your head around hooks
ですので、しばらくお待ちいただいてから、
can be really challenging. So let's come back in a moment
フックを使ったサンプルプロジェクトで作業しましょう。